So we've just seen a short history of AI.
and now the question is where are we now.
We'll, let's let you vote.
We'll do a little quiz. Which of the following things
can we do at present.
Can we create a machine which plays a
decent game of table tennis?
Raise your hands if yes.
Yes.
Can we create a game that plays a decent
game of Jeopardy?
Yes; many of you saw this decent game--it was okay, right, computer did okay.
Okay, we'll actually talk more about Watson later.
Can we build an AI,
that will drive safely along a curving
mountain road? Yes.
Can we build an AI that'll drive safely
along Telegraph Avenue?
I'm not sure *I* can drive safely on
Telegraph Avenue. So the answer is
actually tricky. We'll come back to
autonomous driving
a couple times in this course.
I'm going to put a question mark here--you know
Telegraph Avenue is particularly difficult
and we can't just have a a car which
does everything a human can do.
However, there are autonomous cars out there driving.
They are among us and they have a plan.
In fact we'll talk a little bit about for example
the Google autonomous driving cars, which
under the right circumstances and with
tools that a driver does not have, are in
fact able to drive on real roads. Amazing progress.
One thing that's really cool about this list:
I've been using this list for years, and
kind of every year or two
some "X" turns into a question mark or a
question mark turns into a check.
It's really cool to watch.
Can we build an AI that will buy a week's worth
of groceries on the web.
Yeah, it's kind of almost not even AI right...
Can we build an AI which will buy a
week's worth of groceries at the Berkeley Bowl?
Well that's a little harder right--you've gotta like navigate around carts.
This is probably something that we currently cannot do and this is an
illustration of the decision problem--
What do I buy?
--being tangled up in the action in the
real world which involves like,
not bumping into people with your cart.
To operate in the real world and in an
actual mobile platform often mixes all
this stuff together in a very challenging
way where the decisions you make happen
at multiple levels of abstraction.
Can we build an AI that will discover and
prove a new mathematical theorem.
Raise your hand if yes.
Raise your hand if no.
Okay, so I'm gonna put a question mark. We
can in fact build amazing theorem provers
that can prove new theorems.
Discovery, not so much. Why is this hard? So it turns out that if
I state a theorem and it's true,
we can build automated methods of
proving that they are true through computation.
It's a lot harder to just ask the computer:
Tell me something awesome about algebra I don't know.
Cause it could be like, hey, wait, wait, I got it.
10 + 3 = 13.
You know, it's true! But you don't
know what's interesting so it's very
hard to characterize what makes a theorem interesting.
In some sense it's easier to prove
something that's true
than figure out what should be proven.
Can we build an AI that will converse
successfully with another person for an hour?
It depends a lot on the other person.
Some of you may have heard of ELIZA. We'll talk a little bit about ELIZA when we
talk about natural language later in the
course, but, for most people the answer is
no.
For some people the answer is yes--you
can converse with some of the people for
some of the time, I don't know, but the
point is in general we cannot yet do this.
We cannot yet have computers that
have full conversational ability on any topic
just like a human would.
How about we build an AI that can
perform a surgical operation?
Who says yes.
Okay, raise your hand if you would let
an AI perform a surgical operaton on you.
Would you let an AI remove your
kidney?
Right, okay,
where did all the hands go?
That illustrates one of the issues--the
answer here's a little complicated.
Yeah, we have computer-assisted surgery.
Computers are starting--including some cool
stuff in Pieter Abbeel's group--starting to
be able to tie knots in an automatic way.
You can do things like track the
movement of an eye in eye surgery and things like that.
However,
it is not yet the case, both in
technology and in cultural kind of
willingness to undergo the experiment,
that we're gonna be having computers
swap our kidneys around.
Can we build an AI that can put away the dishes and fold the laundry?
Yeah, we can build it right here at Berkeley.
I will show you a little bit later, again, some of
Pieter's work on folding.
We can do that.
Translate spoken Chinese into spoken English in real time?
Raise your hand if you think we can do it.
Yeah, we'll talk more about translation and real time translation later,
but we can basically do this.
Now you say, wait, is it good English?
Um..., uh..., I didn't say it was good I said it
was spoken right, um...
but we can do real-time
recognition, translation synthesis. That
is something we can do.
Better than you probably think.
Can we build an AI that will write an
intentionally funny story.
Who thinks yes?
Uh...
I'm going to say no.
It's an open area of natural language
processing.